hi ben
thank you so much for making time this
is great um i'm really looking forward
to having this opportunity to
have a conversation with you about
regenerative practice because i think
you're among less than a handful of
people that i would say really
um have an a depth
in and lineage of having worked with
this for
30 40 years and it's something that a
lot of people don't even realize
um because it's such a buzzword at the
moment that um
me included didn't realize how long the
lineage of
the regenesis institute and regenesis
group and carol's work
had actually been stewarding a whole
um set of you like to call it technology
as a set of frameworks and
tools of working with um people on
helping them regenerate
their places and their relationship to
place and and
um unleash their their personal
collective
essences or potential um in the service
to a larger hole
as i have understood it so um
how how did you get into this work um
because you started off as an artist and
also as a permaculture
and landscape gardener a few decades ago
yeah well um
yeah so i studied i studied humanities
and then
i trained to become a painter an artist
um but very early on
i realized that i needed to take that
training and apply it to design if i was
going to make a living
and i grew up in santa fe new mexico
which is it's right at the interface
between
kind of dry desert
grasslands and mountains high mountains
the rocky mountains
and so it's a kind of harsh place
and learning how to garden here and how
to do
landscape designs homes is challenging
um luckily i grew up in
my stepmother was a botanist and she
started the first
native plant nursery here in new mexico
and so i grew up sort of learning how to
work with native species
collect the seeds grow them and so on
and
that was where i really started out i
was always a gardener and always
interested in design
but um the impulse behind doing that
uh native plant work was you know how to
bring
the way we live in this very kind of
fragile
and challenging landscape how to bring
it
into harmony with that landscape using
native species and so on
so that's really where i launched and
i'd always been a big fan
of rodale and the roedale institute and
so on
and through that i became aware of
permaculture
right when the first book was published
in the 70s maybe um and
so i was tracking it but sort of very
busy with my little
you know career and
um then at some point in the
mid seventh or mid 80s uh
i actually met bill mollison
and he was a big charismatic
megafauna kind of guy and he sort of
swept
up a bunch of us in the in new mexico
and and also in arizona and
within a year we had formed something
called permaculture dryland since
two which was about joel uh
what was joel already involved in that
well joel and i went to the same college
so we knew each other
when we were like kids really
yeah and um and we have been friends and
he worked with me in my landscape
company
for some years and then he went off and
specialized in organic agriculture that
became his focus for a while
and we came back together around the
permaculture work
along with other kind of you know tim
murphy who
was practicing in uh southern arizona
with his wife vic margaret
and um and scott pittman who was based
near santa fe and so on anyway it was
kind of an interesting wild west period
in the permaculture movement
and um in the here in
north america there hadn't been a lot of
work yet in dry land so we formed
to really focus on dry lands which meant
that a lot of what we were
interested in was um how
mollison and holmgren were thinking
about water
in relationship you know managing water
and soil
in relationship to establishing
permanent
productive landscapes and
i got very very involved in that spent
some years
you know teaching and and designing and
working in the field
mainly doing contract work for designs
for people
yeah and so on and then doing
permaculture pdc courses and
yeah and
of course as our experience grew and i
you know i teamed up with other people
and as our experience grew both on the
teaching side
and on the consulting side you know we
were able to take on
larger and increasingly sophisticated
projects so we started out
working you know people's backyards that
kind of stuff and small farms
and it grew uh especially after we met
and started working with um
oh now it's uh max um
his name's gone out of my mind he he was
one of the first village developers
max lindager thank you um in australia
uh he we brought him over a few times to
new mexico
yeah and um and at that point we started
getting really excited about village
design and
taking on larger and larger development
projects campus development
and so on and um at some point
i felt like i hit kind of a wall
uh this is a very long-winded way of
sort of saying that
interesting regenesis grew out of the
two streams two schools of thought
really
about what regeneration is and
uh so one of those schools of thought
one of those streams of thinking
came out of robert rodale's work
and um and then especially
bill mollison and to some extent people
like fukuoka and so there was a whole
group
of people around you know the capacity
of human beings to live
uh as um
collaborators and
uh and enablers of the potential of
natural systems
and that so that whole school of thought
uh was working on regeneration mollison
made the distinction between
degenerative generative and regenerative
investments he um called it
course robert rodale was really starting
when he died he was right in the middle
of a deep
investigation into what is regeneration
and what's it all about
and um so that was very very influential
for me
you know when i was younger and uh
but i kept sort of bumping up against a
wall
and i couldn't quite figure out what it
was but
at the time the way i described it is
um we can unders we can understand
how to design these complex
biomimetic landscapes
but the people that we're designing them
for
whether they're individuals or
communities or institutions
don't know how to live in them uh
and so the wall i kept or there was a
wall or a ceiling maybe that i kept
hitting up against was the capacity of
the people that we were or the systems
we were designing
for and i realized that you know
so my kind of default was well let's
just train them up in permaculture and
then they'll get it
but it wasn't working it wasn't enough
and as a result you know a fair number
of the projects that we designed
either never adequately got implemented
or they would be implemented but then
people didn't know how to
grow and evolve and change with them
yeah i mean the
the list of examples as you were
describing this pattern i was just
thinking of
um bedset in london where they tried
this bedding zero emissions initiative
urban eco village in the middle of
london and they had it all planned out
with
one planet living people involved in
this this
architect bill dunster and once people
moved into these structures
you could see that they hadn't thought
of the social dimension of it on how to
onboard people
behaviorally and how to live in them and
and so
some of it worked and some of it didn't
work and yeah
yeah i was i was really uh um
absorbed in or really interested in
a project in uh in california called
village homes that was also a real
david yeah in previous yeah it was a
pioneering project bill mollison was
very enthusiastic about it
and so you had a bunch of permaculture
people associated with that back in the
70s i guess
and um it was the same thing
right very sophisticated in terms of
land use
and management of resources and solar
design and layout of parking and so on
but no not sophisticated enough about
the design
of the culture and governance process
that would allow people to not only
live harmoniously with this what was
built
but to actually continue to evolve it
and as a result it started really
sometime in the i guess it was in the
early 90s i went back there with a group
to have a look at it i've been so
swept away by it when i first visited
and it was really dispiriting um
you know the way all of the fundamental
premises of the design
were being slowly dismantled by you know
second and third generation owners
because
there was no culture to sustain it to
evolve with it
so that it was that was the problem the
way i was seeing it
at the time and in the middle of all of
this i met up with
bob pamela mang who had been deeply
uh immersed in another stream of
thinking
about regeneration that you alluded to
earlier
that had you know that has also been
around since
the late 50s really and it had its roots
in the work of people like david baum
and
um jg bennett and people like that
and they were interested in uh
the application of regenerative
principles to com
to community culture organizational
design and development
and they were part of a group that were
one of the most pioneering
networks of practitioners of
organizational development back at the
you know birth of that movement
studying with a guy named charlie crone
who did really sophisticated work in
some very large
companies and when we met they
immediately recognized that
we were working on something that was
missing in their work that
felt like if they needed it and we
immediately recognized that they had
something that we were missing
which could address the ceiling that we
kept bumping into
and um after i don't know a couple years
of talking about
it and doing projects and trying things
out
we decided to come together and form
regenesis to see
if we could um
integrate or yeah create something new
out of these
bringing these two schools of thought
together was it just
simply coincident or the luck of
um pamela also being in new mexico or
did
how did you actually meet
that's kind of weird i i had been
working
i spent four years working on a really
kind of massive project it was a
it was like a retreat center but very
um exclusive retreat center
um at the home of
the former home of georgia o'keeffe
actually when she lived the
last part of her life she she was in
santa fe
and um pamela brought a group called the
world business academy there
um that had all these kind of luminaries
and
that's where we met and i took this
group
of that she had brought there around and
exposed them to what we were doing
and the underlying philosophy of it and
you know sort of the whole systems
thinking involved in
you know a garden right and um
we had very deliberately designed that
project
to have this effect it would you know
the the retreat center hosted very high
level conferences and gatherings
but in order to use it they had to agree
to go out and walk the grounds with
you know some member of the team that
was working there on the grounds
so they could be exposed to living
systems thinking
in practical application
and uh so i would take these groups
around
and talk to them about how all of these
things work together
and after half an hour an hour they'd
just be like
lit up ecstatic because they could
immediately translate
what was functioning as a metaphor for
them right you know they could
these practical applications in concrete
material terms they could see how it
applied to whatever they were working on
policy business transformation
you know whatever cultural questions
um and so
it was through that interaction that she
said she invited me to dinner she said
wow that was really cool
come meet my husband we hit it off i
introduced them to my colleagues and
you know like i said over a couple year
period
they attended permaculture courses to
find out what we were doing
and um by the end of it we had decided
to form regenesis
and and we at that point like you you
we was um your outfit with joe glansberg
or the the
still the permaculture drylands
institute
well i was still very involved in the
um joel was also a faculty member for
the institute he had his own little
institute going
out at one of the native american
pueblos
nearby so he was pursuing his own line
of work he was primarily interested
in kind of agricultural application and
especially
in indigenous communities right so that
was that had been his focus
whereas we were trying to figure out how
to influence we meaning tim
and and i and several other colleagues
were trying to figure out how to
shift development patterns um
we weren't so much working on urban
systems at that point it was more like
suburban
or village development that kind of
thing and
um but we we continued to work together
through the auspices
of being friends and being in the
permaculture drylands institute
it wasn't until we formed regenesis that
it sort of pulled us all back together
under one roof
bringing you know 10 15 years of
experience from these
different specialties we'd all gone out
and tested
in terms of the application of
permaculture or the application of this
regenerative thinking in organizations
and when we came together we had
huge ambitions about really shifting the
paradigm
with regard to development users
specifically
said okay what are we going to work on
and then looked at the development
sector and then actually went out
to pursue developers to work with you on
new
projects yeah i mean it made sense that
had been our field
right uh was land land use the
even bob uh although he's part of that
network
his primary focus had been first of all
in
land development and secondly working at
very large scales on the
impact of development and how do you
create
governing structures and systems
to manage development kind of
at urban and larger scales so that was
beneficial and not destructive
and i just as you were speaking because
all of this is happening in new mexico
um on not all of it but you you meeting
i just suddenly thought
what have the overlaps been over the
years with the the sort of tribe that
is stewarding the pioneers and and also
when
when they did their dreaming new mexico
projects um
in the and was it um actually that's
that's much more recent
um yeah that was the early 2000s i think
yeah so we were always
friendly with those guys and we actually
did some work
uh we did a story of place process with
them on their property
outside of santa fe and over the years
you know a number of us have spoken at
the big bioneers conferences
and so on um and then when they put
together
the um dreaming new mexico project
uh we hosted that actually we
they they set up an office inside we had
a kind of complex of offices
where a bunch of different you know kind
of like-minded organizations
shared the space together and so
dreaming new mexico set up its offices
inside of our little complex and we
worked with them on it quite a bit
especially
in the initial stages you know around
conceptualization
um so yeah there's been a
there was a lot of kind of cross
fertilization and interaction in those
early years
at some point regenesis became much more
global
in its you know once we'd really
established ourselves
uh we started getting called to do work
all over the world
and um and so santa fe
and it had always been difficult to set
you know profit in his hometown kind of
thing
it had always been difficult to find
work
uh or to be um what taken seriously
here in our own backyard it's partly new
mexico is very very poor
and um and so there's just not all that
much
opportunity um so we we took a stab at
it i mean we worked in a lot of
institutions and continue to work in
institutions in new mexico but
it's a slow process from like in order
to
for me to get a more profitable sense of
a large client in that like as you were
beginning to
find work all over the world and like
every time i've looked into some of the
case studies or the
the projects that you that you speak
about when you explain
how to work regeneratively in the
regenerative
practitioner program for example or in
your book with pamela
and it always feels like
they're quite long-term large projects
that require a level of buy-in
by some form of client
the developer or the wider community
that isn't in itself so easily come by
how do you make that engagement and are
all these projects projects where
we're really from the outset people say
we're going to be with you for at least
two years or two and a half three years
and this is a process
and you better be ready for it and sign
the dotted line
that that we're committed to this or
have they also been kind of like let's
just engage and see where this is going
type of pro
approaches some of some some all of the
above
and you know obviously we started out
doing tiny projects i mean
i started out as like a little gardener
and sort of built it over a very long
period of time
and that in itself i think may be
relevant because
because we were working from a
um a technology a fairly sophisticated
set of principles
frameworks ways of thinking what i could
learn
on a very small scale then could be
applied
you know as i took on more and more
ambitious
uh more and more complex projects right
the same
the same underlying principles and
ways of thinking applied just the
complexity grew
right what you had to be able to embrace
and understand got more and more
difficult to hold
and so we had to grow into that um it
with regard to
your ques it's a it's a kind of an
insider's question daniel this thing
about
how do you how do you engage somebody
and
ideally you engage with them um
with full consciousness of what they're
getting into
right they may not know what's actually
going to happen or how it's going to
work but they
they do need to know that this is a
developmental process
if it's to um realize all of its
potential
and um but does doesn't that mean that
you very
like precisely because we live in a
culture that
that tends to kind of be very
solutioneering
and and and problem solution
implementation
focused um when you then say okay no we
we really want to do a series of
interviews and really get close to the
story of place through different
perspectives of people
involved in this area and and then begin
a process of
mirroring back to them what you've heard
them speak to about the place to to get
closer to
to a a shared access to the deeper
essence of
of what what what are you actually
working with um
isn't isn't that very often than quite a
tension with a
client like a developer of saying well
we just wanted to
build 400 units and we have problems
with these guys who are saying
that it's a wetland that we shouldn't
touch um
and we just want to resolve that issue
and like how
how do you dance with that is that me
projecting something into it that
doesn't doesn't happen
oh no it happens all the time and um
to some extent i think as we've
matured right and gotten clearer and
clearer about what
we we had to invent this as we went
along i couldn't speak
with this level of confidence 15 years
ago
[Music]
so we went out and made every mistake
you can make and learn from them and you
know had
some successes and some i don't know if
they're
ever failures because everyone learns
from the process
but more and more
uh one it's like you can begin to
discern who has
the readiness if you will
to recognize that just simply you know
patching the hole or fixing the problem
is not enough uh and
particularly you know so if they're kind
of
small or wildcat developers who just
have one-off projects
that's less likely unless they're super
super inspired
to want to pursue you know they have
some very large aspiration about the
quality of what they're doing
right it's the people who have really
dedicated their lives to the work so
they're they're continually in the
process
of working on creating better and more
successful projects they're the ones
where you have the potential to learn
with them so any individual project
no project is ever going to be perfect
there is no such
thing as perfect but every project can
become
an opportunity to move up to the next
level
um and
so that's one way of answering a
question another way of answering a
question is
we would not have gotten off the ground
if this were not incredibly effective
as a way to create successful projects
and um often the effectiveness is kind
of indirect
so for example um one of the core things
that we
articulate now i'm speaking strictly in
the arena of
land development at the moment
land development is uh has become
a really um i don't know degraded
profession uh it's highly for the most
part it's highly degenerate it's very
very destructive
practice and for on for the most part
and so people for good reason often are
really resistant
when a developer wants to come in and
like do their fabulous
shiny whatever it is subdivision
or office tower and
uh so one of the things that
they are faced with is how do we engage
a community that's resistant to what we
want to do
in a way that they will embrace it
because if they embrace it the project
for multiple reasons project's more
likely to be successful
right you've got kind of a welcoming
environment
um you have a willingness to work with
the
with the developer around approvals and
all of that stuff
and that those are the biggest risks and
hurdles for a developer
is you know am i going to get the
entitlement am i going to be approved to
do this project
uh in in something that's
more or less likely to be viable and
uh the key to all of this
is that for a developer to successful
this from our perspective
for a developer to successfully engage a
community
the developer needs to be willing to
join with the community
to achieve its larger aspirations
so it's not about talking the community
into supporting me
it's about joining with the community
to help the community evolve to become
more of what it
wants and needs to be and that will
always end up
shaping what the project ends up being i
mean it sounds
wonderful and from from everything that
that i've sort of been involved in
i would like the thoughts that come up
is that
again there's a selection process of how
do you
as you engage the community you have to
commit to
what was most likely going to be a
slower process because it is actually
listening
to place and sourced from place and
pattern by place
and that takes time to engage in a
certain process before you
before you pull out the plans and
or the willingness to to say we started
with these plans and now that we've done
this process
we're actually going to despite the fact
that we invested in having people work
on these plans
rip them up and draw new plans and all
of that
is ultimately making things a bit more
expensive
um in the short term probably has
huge financial benefits in the long term
but it's precisely that where most
projects today
have that have the difficulty connecting
the systemic longer vision and the
systemic
positive impacts with the conversation
with one or two
clients that um that just
say like we have a pipeline and we want
to get on to the next project um
any kind of well it's
it's actually it turns out to be just
the opposite that um
that um by it's you know that
truism that the japanese introduced
around go slow to go fast um
that the the more time you spend at the
very before you ever actually put a
drawing
down right the more time you spend
understanding what this particular
ecosystem landscape community is all
about
right what uh what it's trying to become
how our project could relate to that and
then building relationships
in the community with you know people
who are respected in the community
around you know this project being an
investment in the community the faster
the whole process goes
it really it can cut years off of
years and just countless amounts of
litigation
uh off of a process and we've seen that
over and over and over again
uh and it it takes a certain amount of
sophistication on the part of the
developer to understand this
right the shift from doing a kind of
linear process
that's about basically um
manipulating public opinion
trying to manage the you know manage the
approvals process and so on uh versus
actually engaging
with the community to become um
you know a trusted investor in that
community uh and that
you know bill love bill reid loves
telling the story about a huge project
that we were working on down in
vina del mar in chile where they were
looking at a minimum
of 10 years being tied up in the courts
with a high likelihood of the project
it was such a big um impactful project
of the project being
disallowed at the end of that years and
years of litigation
and um he and tim
within two weeks of community engagement
were able to completely
change turn that around right
so 10 years of litigation with a high
likelihood of failure
two weeks of community engagement which
required the developer
to say okay we're willing to
we're willing to actually engage meaning
this is not about you know window
dressing going out there and pretending
to people that we're your friends
this is about actually saying um
we're we recognize that the reason
the deeper reason we want to develop
this project is to bring life back to
this city
and that we need to work with you and we
need to build relationships of trust
collaboration purposefulness
to be able to accomplish that and it's
been transformational for the company
for the um communities surrounding this
massive project
for the you know for the city so
earlier you spoke about these two
streams um coming together and you then
forming regenesis how did your work
since you were mainly in one of those
two streams how did your work
change once the pieces that pamela
um and and folks brought in were added
um what what transformed yeah
so i said that um we
kept bumping into the ceiling where the
the client group whatever it was the
system that we were designing for
uh wasn't able to
[Music]
absorb and work with the designs the
actual
functioning designs that we were giving
them and
um
over time what i came to realize
is that uh the core thing
that needed to be worked on was the way
people were thinking
um that it uh
it wasn't about any particular topic
any particular project any particular
problem or issue that
people were trying to address that it
had to do with
the way the basic structure of the way
they were thinking uh and that that was
if we wanted to move we went into land
development
because we saw it having an enormous
impact on the planet and that if we
could
move the dial with regard to that
it could you know it could really make a
difference
but over the over the years i've
become increasingly aware that where you
move the dial is in the way people are
thinking
and so that and the idea is to build
capacity in people's thinking
everybody's thinking so that the choices
that we're making
individually and collectively are
choices that are regenerative that are
harmonious
with you know with the planet with place
um
one of the things that was invisible to
me
when i was practicing permaculture and
it's taken a long time for me to realize
is that the reason that was so difficult
to do from within the permaculture
kind of milieu was that it's
uh functional in its orientation
right the and that's the way mollison
characterized it he talked about
functional landscapes
meaning as opposed to dysfunctional
landscapes right
landscapes that have been robbed of
their ability to function
and uh there was always some sense that
we needed to pay attention to
the social and cultural systems around
that
but there wasn't a whole lot of
understanding of how to work on that
right other than let's see if we can
apply
these functional things that we've
learned about designing landscapes to
functionally designing community
governance or whatever
and by leaving
by focusing on function what gets left
out in there
is the sense of being and of will right
how do you actually cultivate or awaken
collective will political will
you know if the this kind of what's
behind your question earlier if the will
isn't present you know it doesn't matter
how great my design is
you know if the developer does not have
the will
to transform the way they are thinking
and working
we can give them great ideas till the
cows come home
it won't ultimately make any difference
and if people aren't able to
kind of manage their own thinking
right and see that as a critical place
to intervene in the system
you remember danella meadows and
paradigms right
that um that if if we don't develop the
capacity
of a community to like pause reflect
right and make better choices
um you get
things like the current response to the
pandemic going on here in the u.s
so
that i don't want to make an
artificial uh or false distinction
between
doing and being or at taking action
functional action and thinking about it
right the two are seamless
right uh what i'm what i'm saying
is that if we want to really transform
the way we're working and inhabiting the
planet
we need to become more intelligent about
the actions that we take
there are a lot of people that are
really gung-ho about going out and
taking actions to
um to fix all kinds of
problems clean up plastic waste in the
oceans
and you know change transportation
networks and all of that stuff it's
great
right uh how do we use every action that
we take to build our intelligence
about systemic interventions
and in in that case because one one of
the things that i found a lot of
resident
or resonance with when when digging
deeper into
the regenesis work um is
your conception of nested wholeness and
and
what is place like place from the place
in front of me but place
being fractal in a way that whatever i
do to the place in front of me
also affects the the entire nested
wholeness
so it affects the planet and then i just
recently watched
um a presentation that you gave in in um
i think denver colorado in 2017 and
we actually spoke to the fact that this
nestedness
is why working regener
regeneratively even at the small scale
with a small group of people in a small
project has efficacy
or agency um beyond that little project
um how would you
like in in terms of advising people what
scale
like is there a scale at which
things get too complicated and too messy
to really have
feedback on what you're doing and
therefore there is actually some
like in order to to wisely stir
into an evolving future that is
uncertain um
are we better off working at local and
regional scales because
feedback is quicker um simply for that
reason
or um or do you think it's actually
possible to have
this approach apply at all scales of
that nested wholeness
it approaches it it applies at all
scales
um so it's like
it's almost the right question but not
quite let me see if i can reframe it
slightly
um
so you're right that the issue is
complexity
but the reason it's an issue is because
of our ability
to manage complexity
uh and so uh
there it there are
one of the reasons that we've focused
from the very beginning on place
is it was a scale of system
that was complex enough that you can
work systemically
i mean and have huge systemic
consequences and yet it's small enough
that people first of all can understand
it
and more importantly they can relate to
how would you define place then because
place seems to be
very different scales yeah it's all
everything's a place yeah right so
planet earth happens to be a place
within our solar system
um and so
we tend to think about plate
it's a so we tend to work with this idea
of place
for most people in most contexts we work
on it at a kind of cultural scale
meaning what does the local culture
recognize as being the natural boundary
of what it takes into account
so if you look at indigenous cultures
those things are laid out very clearly
you know they're often laid out in terms
of very specific
landmarks you know and
naturally occurring phenomena rivers
mountains and so on
uh within urban
systems you know there's people kind of
know where their neighborhood boundary
is within small towns people know where
the watershed boundary is
they may not given those they may not
think about it much they just sort of
know
i live in this part of town right i live
in this
i live in this part of new mexico right
and i know immediately when i'm no
longer in my part of new mexico
um because i grew up here you just know
uh so a lot of
what we do in a given context is try and
understand or suss out
where that kind of collective agreement
is
about this is ours this is what we care
about
you know over there is over there but
here is here
and uh because if we can understand that
and identify it it's much much easier to
work
on that question of will what is it that
people
really love really care about really are
willing to do something about if they
saw
that there was some possibility of doing
it
um so that's one way of thinking about
place
yeah as different people are going to
see that at different levels some people
need to keep it very
bounded and close in other people can
see it in a very large sense
but the key is can i relate to it
do can i actually feel caring for it
not as an intellectual thing but as
something that i
i know and understand and am willing
to dedicate myself to this
um this something else to say
and and then once i've got that bounded
then i can understand its nestedness i
know
how i'm fit inside of it and i know
how it fits you know in
whatever the next system is uh so
if i just arbitrarily talk about my own
town i sort of know
my town which fits is pretty well
bounded by and defined by a particular
watershed
and i know kind of where that watershed
ends and
how that fits within a region that we
call north northern new mexico or
north central new mexico and it's it's a
very distinctive
cultural geological ecological region
so i can immediately see you know how
things fit together um
this understanding of nessa because we
started out in
kind of i started as a gardener we
started out in the field of land
development
place became the thing that we focused
on
it's a really really useful concept
for working on the relationship of
people in ecological systems
which is one of the huge topics in the
world at the moment
however the pattern behind it the way of
thinking behind it applies to
any field so just to
make sure that i understood you there
and i think because this is a really
important point that
for me it's been a journey like i'm
testing something out here
with my own work on mallorca um
the nested hole that
well the the proximate hole that in
order to shift something
in the patterns on this island
drawn from the deep
recognition of people here that there's
something unique about mallorca that
that only majorca can
give to the world that is beyond
um what the knee-jerk
response might be right now um well
some sex in sangria or whatever they
advertise cheap mass tourism
um with but is is the uniqueness of this
this this particular location and its
history and so on um working
with mallorca it it's not always that i
then have to say oh the nested hole of
course is the balearic islands and then
it sits in southern europe or in spain
and then it sits in europe
which would be the entire sort of linear
geographical nestedness
um but it could be that
working on mallorca you're actually
working on the transformation of tourism
and and that that transformation of
tourism then would also help the
transformation
of this island am i getting it
sort of i mean if you're if you're
working on tourism
right then working on tourism in
mallorca as a way of working on tourism
generally yeah so
you could say there is an entity
called tourism in mallorca right that
you
are choosing to care about right and
you're choosing to evolve it
just as there is an entity called land
development in mallorca that you're
choosing to do something about
and uh so
and the same would be true of i'm just
trying to think of
wine for example right
that if your passion is wine right
understanding and developing the way
wine happens on mallorca
compared to wine in a larger spanish or
southern european context right
that wine's an easy example because it's
fun
it is inherently place based right one
of the things that
makes wine so popular is that it
actually can express
the distinctiveness of the place so when
you work on wine you're inherently also
working on the place
if you're doing something other than
mass-produced you know
low-grade
stuff um
so the the point
is
that what distinguish the pattern behind
what we're doing around place
is we're trying to understand who is
this place what is its essence
what is its unique character uh
because that's the thing people are
relating to so would you say that again
because like i i looked up
your bio briefly um and one of them that
pops up is the one that you've got on
the regenesis webpage and in it you say
you
you specialize in holistic systems-based
approach to understanding
and building upon the complex human
natural and economic relationships
that create and sustain the vitality and
viability
of a place and
that resonates very strongly with me
that's what i would say
i came to mallorca to do that very thing
to learn how to do that and at the time
my experience of having tried to do
similar things
in experimental communities equal
villages or with
small subgroups of the willing in a
particular place
transition town groups and so on let me
personally
at the time to an insight that to really
create
systemic change where
you could leverage certain economics of
scale and
and provide certain needs for a regional
population
brought me more and more or closer and
closer to
regional scale of work and that's why i
moved
to mallorca 10 years ago because i
thought okay i want to
commit to place anyway for my own sake
and lifestyle and
grounding and myocar is a great place
to study what one can do
over the long term humbly to
do systemic acupuncture and help
create conversations and projects that
slowly
contribute hopefully in a catalytic way
um to the positive transformation of a
place
is is that in and of itself
mistaken to some extent to just because
because then the question there is if
you do that in one
island of the mediterranean of course
every other island will be different but
there is this
question to what extent can you can you
transfer
patterns and processes that you learn in
one place by regionally to then
build networks with other islands that
are on the same journey and
if at least form peer support groups
that
that where people can we come across a
similar project
problems and this is how we work around
them but also
to inspire anybody in the mediterranean
climate zone
that at the regional scale
it is possible to revitalize
social relationships economic
relationships and ecological
relationships in such a way
that um everybody in that place wins and
you actually build resilience against
climate change and all sorts of other
uncertainties coming at us um
in what way is is that whole framing
not aligned with with the way that you
would work
regeneratively so you you could tell
that it wasn't
aligned right well i know i know you're
well enough and we
often enough that i know that so
everything that you said makes sense
it's accurate and it's characteristic
of a lot of work that's being done out
there
around ideas like sustainability
resilience even permaculture is a very
characteristic way of thinking within a
permaculture context
right and
so i'm going to try and slow this down
so we can really get to it if we can
um that
you're describing
the system of majorca as an it
right and and and you made it a
you know it's a great it it's beautiful
it's
you know has these it's just an amazing
place right
um
and but looked at from that point of
view
there are any number of islands you
could have chosen
to work on in a similar way right you
know so if i thought about it in those
terms if i was really kind of
shopping around and deciding which
island am i going to do this on
you know i'd make lists and i'd sort of
weigh the
pros and cons and i'd select the one
that worked best for me
i'm guessing that uh
in the 10 years that you've lived in
mallorca
something else has happened and in fact
may have already happened before you
made the choice
which is you also feel drawn to it
yeah i mean that is you can actually
relate to it
and that relatedness that sense of being
at home
or um i really care about this place
you know i love the relationships i'm
building here
i love the way it feels to take that
particular walk and see that mountain in
that particular way
all of that stuff you know is happening
it's the distinction i mentioned earlier
there's a functional way of looking at
it
and there's a being way of looking at it
but
for me in my experience of how i've done
this work now for 10 years
is that while i might have looked at
functional issues and made lists of
transformation and agriculture and
energy and
transport sector and urban development
and
all sorts of potential for transforming
the
dominant economy which is of course
tourism
but i feel that the the way of actually
working with it for example bringing
a whole group of local people together
working around the project
where echo belgium detergent company
wanted to
explore um the production of
soaps and cleaning products from local
waste products
for me and and you mentioned this
alluded to this earlier with some
projects were successful in some
projects
is it you basically didn't say that
they also had their successes even if
maybe
what the main aim was wasn't successful
because
it they introduced a way of thinking
with people and in a similar way
i feel like a lot of the projects both
educational programs i've brought here
work with universities work with this
different like corporate clients
they all invite that kind of
conversation maybe less structured but
but they create that conversation about
what really matters about this play how
is this place unique
what are from what what is the potential
here in terms of
unused resources that we can
um connect and unuse connections between
people
that that would unleash potential um
can i can i pause you right here so
i was tracking you and then you fell off
a little cliff right
um all i'm trying to do is make explicit
um this distinction between
functional development and development
of being
because our premise is that when you
work them
together you get a completely different
kind of result
completely different level of
effectiveness
and so
i can think about the
development of the potential of a place
in terms of translating underutilized
resources
into some kind of productive
new use right or i can
yeah human relationship and that's
that's a perfectly legitimate
way of working on it um but it's
one-sided
and the other way of looking at it is
the potential of this place
has to do with um
allowing its
essence its soul to manifest more fully
into the world
[Music]
and the reason that's and so you're
right
it is people do care about the places
they live and when you gather a group
that has an
interest in working something like the
zero waste initiative it's there it's
implicit
right and certain kinds of conversations
will lift it up
but if the conversations are not
conceived
in in a developmental way
then they don't actually build
people's ability to conceptualize
the um
you know that aspect
of the potential of what they're working
on
and that ends up making a huge
difference
in terms of what what they end up being
able to
enact like
because we've only got about 15 minutes
left or so
and i'm going to try something zooming
out this might or might not
not work because it relates very much um
to this
earlier briefly alluded to donnella
meadows and the leverage points paper
and i i had a look and i'm still working
on
and i would love to have a another
conversation separate with um
about this paper that you wrote recently
with carol sanford on
a framework for working on economics
regeneratively
um and in that you also bring up the
leverage points and you bring up that
places to intervene
and and you frame it in a way that she
did in her first version of that paper
um
where the highest point is um
to intervene at the level of the
paradigm and at that point when she
wrote it she framed it
around that that's the fundamental sort
of cuny and paradigm shift and
everything else changes
the whole understanding of the system
changes and
and when she first wrote it she did the
same thing as you do in that paper which
is to say
um paradigms are mutually exclusive and
so once you're in that new paradigm you
see things completely differently
um but donna herself
in the later part of her life
then rewrote that paper and added
another level to it which
is um the highest leverage point is
moving beyond paradigms
and what i think she was alluding to and
bringing that close to
regenerous language would be that
what she was saying is that in order to
p pick
people up and keep the conversation
going as you dance with complexity and
systems
and you keep all the levels of work
open at the same time and
you can actually work and then
and i i'm noticing that of course the
the the long apprenticeship and practice
to really work
purely regeneratively and and train your
mind and your ability to do it is a long
deep journey and i have a long way to go
there but i guess where i
sometimes bump into
wanting to keep learning from
those technologies and how to apply them
but then
i where i don't see eye to eye where
there's a different perspective maybe is
is that i actually believe that as you
say yourself
that all the other levels of work are
also really important and they all
you in for a system to stay viable
and evolving and and all that it needs
to actually
do all the levels of work um and so for
for me
the question is when when working in
these ways don't we
over time bring sometimes
in the right moment with the right
people for the right amount of time the
deeper
regenerative level work into the
conversation
as we capture people and engage them
because some of the finance flows and
decision makers
might not quite be ready for that
conversation yet but so they get drawn
in
to a project that that is actually
working on maintain level
um or improve level but is um
is keeping at least aspirationally and
and
and in terms of energetic holding the
the regenerate
like the evolutionary dimension the
development
dimension open does that make any sense
whatsoever like do you get
what i'm trying like do you understand
what i'm trying to ask
uh yeah and so here here's how i would
say it back to you um that
with my own little twist on it that um
that the we tend to
work within the regenerative within the
genesis
you know frame we talk about five levels
of work
right all of which need to be present uh
if
an entity is to remain vital viable and
capable of evolution
yeah and the bottom level is stabilized
right so if you get a wound it can heal
right uh you know the body's you know
you get a flu
the body needs to heal itself but once
you've got that then you can move
into these other levels and um
being able to uh understand
and think and work from those different
levels of work
requires development right
so people enter at various levels in
terms of their
the existing capacity they've developed
what they're just naturally able to do
and the idea is to continually help them
extend and expand
their thinking so that they can hold the
whole
of a dynamic living changing evolving
operating system
um yeah so obviously i mean regeneration
has to do the way i inve you know image
it uh
regeneration is about going back to the
essence of something and bringing it
forward in a new way
as the world is changing right so if you
keep on doing what you've always done
and the world is changing around you you
become
most things become decreasingly viable
right so they have to sort of take that
core
genius whether it's genetic or you know
in terms of essence or or nature or
character
and sort of bring it into a new
situation a new context and that's
that's how we grow and develop as human
beings from
you know infancy on to the end of our
lives
so yes of course it's completely
appropriate to engage people where
they're at it would be disrespectful not
to engage people
where they're at while holding
it's equally disrespectful to not
hold the assumption and expectation that
they can grow from where they're
at whoever they are yeah
everyone you know this is this is why
it's completely
appropriate to involve children in
decision-making processes
you know that have to do with the body
politic is completely appropriate
right understanding that they're at a
certain stage in their development but
they
also need to be growing along with the
rest of us
um
the way i hear sort of your
comment on the on danella meadows
evolution and her thinking the way i
hear that is a recognition
that um
that beyond paradigm
right uh there is an ability to look at
where and how paradigms are sourced
right
so we talk about paradigm as kind of the
frame of reference within which we live
you know sort of how we frame and
understand reality
but it's possible to step out of that
and say okay what is the process by
which
reality framing is occurring
and what do i need to what do i need to
be able to observe in myself
and then observe in my cosmos
to be able to look at that uh
and so i was thinking about this coming
into this conversation that
these levels of work is not the whole
game
right there are levels of work below and
levels of work beyond
what we talk about you know regeneration
is a particular level of work it's not
the end of the story
it just happens to be a level of work
that we collectively need to learn how
to do
you know and uh
and there's not a huge capacity out
there
you know yet to be able to think at that
level
there's not even that much capacity to
be able to think
uh at the evolution of systems level
when
like briefly coming back to donella's
point there um
i'm wondering whether it's it what she
was trying to get it or the way i've
often interpreted her is that yes
it's understanding the very
participation participatory nature of
mind in
in mattering literally like in creating
reality
bringing forth a world together in
relationship all those
kind of frames that madorana and varila
and all those people brought into
this more dynamic evolutionary way of
thinking
about evolving systems
and i i believe that she was also
speaking to a more developmental
approach
in terms of the kind of stages of human
development psja
or gaps or spiral dynamics or wilbur or
whatever you want to
um use as a frame that that
we also need to keep the older paradigms
so to speak um
[Music]
healthy in their expression because as
people
evolve and gain deeper and deeper
understanding of the participatory
nature of
the world as long as we still teach
newtonian physics and stuff
the predisposition to fall into this
object subject separation world and all
that will be there and so we need to
have the paradigms
all offer their unique
and useful contribution as
a perspective of participation in
continuously transforming wholeness um
but not the perspective so learning
like taking even if they are because in
that
paper that that you wrote you say
they're incommensurable
but that means in one moment you can't
hold two paradigms at once
but you can learn from one perspective
and then you can
shift perspective and learn from the
other perspective and then you can build
wise action in dynamic
wholeness in understanding that each
perspective has blind spots
and so being informed by multiple
perspectives might
offer um paths to wiser
that's that's how i understood that
okay well i i think it's an interesting
thing to
to investigate um i i'm skeptical
what makes you skeptical well i
because
i mean if i just look at myself
personally
i'm perfectly capable of dropping down
to a value return
paradigm i do it daily right
uh it's like what's in it for me you
know you you want this
what's in it for me why would i bother
you know engaging in this
interaction um
and uh
my experience of stepping out of that
kind of level of consciousness is that
um when i have stepped out of it
i view having been in it as regressive
meaning that it's not that
i'm no longer ext in exchange with my
environment
it's just that what's in it for me is no
longer
it's like it's no longer
a question that uh needs to orient
or you know um
shape the choices that i'm making
so i don't mean to be belittling or
denigrating
um people operating in different
different paradigms i mean we're
surrounded by people operating from
different paradigms
it's not that it's that i my sense is
what it and it's not about perspective
right uh it's about um which
reality am i moving through
in my life right and to what extent have
i developed my ability
to operate from within a reality
that um is life generating
so uh
so again for me i kind of get where your
question is coming from
and i can see how you're trying to
create a parallel between that and the
idea of levels of work all of which need
to be
you know healthy and dynamically related
and so on
um but it's not my experience that it
works that way
that i experience myself
almost as a different person
when i'm operating from a higher order
paradigm
the the me who shows up the i who shows
up is a different nature of i
you know i i guess
for me it comes from from an experience
of having tried to build bridges
between people who come from very
different um
perspectives for a very long time and
well that having had that experience
that sometimes you just need to
it doesn't mean that you yourselves
change your being state
from like suddenly collapsing
an understanding of dynamic
participatory wholeness where mind is
involved
in shaping matter um down to
or now i'm talking to somebody who's
trapped in a newtonian
physics paradigm so so therefore i
collapse into that too
but i can use my language
and even build three steps on a
10 000 step journey with them using that
that's totally necessary that's this
word developmental that we just throw
around and throw around and throw around
that's what that's supposed to mean
countering someone who i experience as
being kind of trapped in
too narrow a cage right um
it would be disrespectful of me to write
them off as being just
that's who that's it trapped is their
destiny
right you know so how do i engage them
in a conversation that allows them
to tap into what it is they really want
to accomplish
uh and to find ways to
to begin to move toward that you know
that
you know we we talked about that in
terms of caring
we sometimes have this conversation
around the difference between compassion
which is wanting people
you know seeing that people are
suffering and wanting to remove their
suffering
and caring which is seeing the inherent
potential in every living being
every human being every living being and
and really wanting to help them like
express that because it's a drive in all
of us
right and so if our paradigm or our way
of viewing the world
or our way of thinking is
um is like
a barrier to being able to express that
potential
then you know it's our responsibility to
one another to help one another
like dismantle those barriers
not everybody is particularly driven to
dismantle those barriers
you know not everybody's interested in
these conversations
but a lot of people are i mean it's it's
amazingly it it's i think
i experience it as deeply respectful and
i think other people
experience it as deeply respectful when
someone is willing to listen
deeply into enough into what they aspire
to be and to become
to want to help them no
it's not about imposing my world view
it's about trying to see what it is that
people are trying to accomplish
not just material but through the luck
through their lives through the meaning
in their lives
um and and to
commit to helping them you've modeled
exactly that with just giving me the
time for this
conversation of the last uh 70 80
minutes
and i i'm a slow learner it seems but
but i think we got to
got to some interesting important points
for me to
there there's just i'm noticing how some
things trigger me
about around the the clear definition of
border this is regenerative and this
isn't and
like it feels that there's so many
friends in the work um that
that are doing wonderful work
and want to dig deeper into
understanding
how to be more effective in working
regeneratively that that i
i often find that i want to make the
bridge for them easier
to not feel just because you're
working by regionally or you're working
with biomimicry you haven't got it yet
or um
it sometimes comes across to people like
that
but but i i see how every time i have
conversations with you
um or with bill or pamela i learn
huge amounts so thank you so much for
this and i wish we could continue but
but i think you have another call
and maybe we'll do another one sometime
soon
thanks daniel thanks for thanks for
doing this
it's really fun it's great way to wake
up
for you for me because when the
hot time of the year now i'm noticing
that these these conversations
um with americans that are fresh early
in the morning it's still cool outside
and me here
sweating in mallorca uh slightly
imbalanced because i'm kind of
at the low point of the day but this was
wonderful and
and i just feel that these
conversational
um recordings i've also had some
feedback from people they really help
people get into this
in a different way than than kind of uh
asking people to
give a half hour lecture and and so on
so
thank you so much for being available
and i hope we'll
do another one and i'm sure we'll see
each other soon in another
call okay okay bye